Dr. Amreesh D. Phokeer

CONTACT Information phokeer@isoc.org--amreesh.phokeer@gmail.com

https://amreesh.github.io

RESEARCH INTERESTS My research interests are in the broad area of computer networking, security, and telecommunication policy, with an emphasis on Internet measurements. I am focused on efforts around designing new tools and techniques to study the global health of the Internet including Internet resilience, routing security issues, Internet shutdowns, and other market trends that impact the growth of the Internet.

Areas of Expertise Web and network performance, Internet protocols, Internet Policy Formulation, Risk Assessment, Team and Project Leadership.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Computer Science, University of Cape Town Supervisory Committee: David Johnson, Melissa Densmore, Nick Feamster

Research Areas: Internet performance in developing regions, peering, interconnection,

Internet measurements

M.Sc. in Information Security, Royal Holloway, University of London 2013

Advisor: Keith Martin

Thesis: RPKI adoption challenges (Pass with Distinction)

Diplôme d'Ingénieur (M.S.), Telecom Nancy (Concours Mines-Télécom) 2008

Work Experience

Internet Society (ISOC)

Internet Measurement and Data Expert

2021 to present

2021

Currently leading the Measuring the Internet (Pulse) project at ISOC. I am a Subject Matter Expert in the areas of Internet shutdowns, Internet concentration, Internet resilience, Internet Governance and Internet policy. Designed and built the Internet Resilience Index. Also leading the Pulse Research fellowship program.

African Network Information Center (AFRINIC)

Research Manager 2014 to 2021 Software Engineering Manager 2011 to 2014

Responsible for Internet security and measurement research projects. Collaborated with a team of international researchers to conduct in-depth Internet measurement campaigns to better understand the African Internet Infrastructure development and challenges from security, performance, and economic perspectives. Managed the AFRINIC research program to foster relationships with academic institutions. Designed and implemented the DNSSEC and RPKI infrastructure at AFRINIC.

National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)

Guest Researcher 2008 to 2010

Assisted Computational biologists in developing tools and techniques for better image analysis. Integrated legacy applications into modern image processing tools. Developed

a project management portal to help researchers keep track of project deliverables, finance and other resources.

COMMUNITY Organizing Committee Membership
WORK ACM COMPASS - Industry and Practition

ACM COMPASS - Industry and Practitioner co-chair

EAI Africomm - General Chair

2023

Program Committee Membership

 USENIX SECURITY
 2022, 2023

 ACM IMC
 2019, 2020

 PAM
 2022

 TMA IFIP
 2021

 ACM SIGCOMM CCR (Additional)
 2020

 ACM AINTEC
 2022, 2023

 JSys Journal
 2022 - Present

Other Forums

GFCE Research Committee - Member 2020, 2021

Mauritius Cybersecurity Committee - Member 2023 - Present

Mauritius Internet Exchange Point Board - Vice Chairman 2022 - Present

Publications

Journal

Sen, R., Ahmad, S., **Phokeer, A.**, Farooq, Z.A., Qazi, I.A., Choffnes, D. and Gummadi, K.P., 2017. Inside the Walled Garden: Deconstructing Facebooks Free Basics Program. ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review, 47(5). [BEST CCR AWARD]

Conference

- 1. Ioana Livadariu (Simula Metropolitan), Romain Fontugne (IIJ Research Laboratory), **Amreesh Phokeer** (Internet Society), Massimo Candela (NTT), Massimiliano Stucchi (AS58280). A tale of two synergies: Uncovering RPKI practices for RTBH at IXPs. Passive and Active Measurement Conference 2024.
- 2. Holterbach, T., Alfroy, T., **Phokeer, A.**, Dainotti, A. and Pelsser, C., A System to Detect Forged-Origin BGP Hijacks. In 21st USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI 24)
- 3. Li, W., Lin, Z., Ashiq, M.I., Aben, E., Fontugne, R., **Phokeer, A.** and Chung, T., 2023, October. RoVista: Measuring and Analyzing the Route Origin Validation (ROV) in RPKI. In Proceedings of the 2023 ACM on Internet Measurement Conference (pp. 73-88).
- 4. Fontugne, Romain; **Phokeer, Amreesh**; Pelsser, Cristel; Vermeulen, Kevin; Bush, Randy; RPKI Time-of-flight: tracking delays in the management and data planes, Passive and Active Measurement Conference 2023.
- 5. Johnson, D., Cloete, L., Hadzic, S., Kiden, S., Rens, A. and **Phokeer, A.**, 2022. African Open Source Digital Infrastructures: Evaluating the Landscape.
- Hemanthindra, A., Phokeer, A., Ramsurrun, V., Katsina, P., Anantwar, S. and Seeam, A.K., 2020, December. DNSSEC as a service - A prototype implementation. In 2020 32nd International Conference on Microelectronics (ICM) (pp. 1-4). IEEE.

- 7. Arouna, A., **Phokeer, A.** and Elmokashfi, A., 2021. A first look at the Africans ccTLDs technical environment. In 12th EAI International Conference, AFRICOMM 2020, December 2-4, 2020, Proceedings 12 (pp. 305-326).
- 8. Akanho, Y., Alassane, M., Houngbadji, M. and **Phokeer, A.**, 2021. African nameservers revealed: characterizing DNS authoritative nameservers. In 12th EAI International Conference, AFRICOMM 2020, December 2-4, 2020, Proceedings 12 (pp. 327-344).
- 9. Kristoff, John; Bush, Randy; Kanich, Chris; Michaelson, George; **Phokeer, Amreesh**; Schmidt, Thomas C; Whlisch, Matthias; On Measuring RPKI Relying Parties, Proceedings of the ACM Internet Measurement Conference 484-491 2020
- 10. Phokeer, Amreesh; Chavula, Josiah; Johnson, David; Densmore, Melissa; Tyson, Gareth; Sathiaseelan, Arjuna; Feamster, Nick; On the potential of Google AMP to promote local content in developing regions, 2019 11th International Conference on Communication Systems & Networks (COMSNETS) 80-87 2019 IEEE
- Isah, Musab; Phokeer, Amreesh; Chavula, Josiah; Elmokashfi, Ahmed; Asrese, Alemnew Sheferaw; State of internet measurement in Africa-A survey, International Conference on e-Infrastructure and e-Services for Developing Countries, 121-139, 2019 Springer, Cham
- 12. Formoso, Agustin; Chavula, Josiah; **Phokeer, Amreesh**; Sathiaseelan, Arjuna; Tyson, Gareth; Deep diving into africa's inter-country latencies, IEEE INFOCOM 2018-IEEE Conference on Computer Communications 2231-2239 2018 IEEE
- 13. Calandro, Enrico; Chavula, Josiah; **Phokeer, Amreesh**; Internet development in Africa: a content use, hosting and distribution perspective, International Conference on e-Infrastructure and e-Services for Developing Countries 131-141 2018 Springer, Cham
- 14. Chavula, Josiah; Phokeer, Amreesh; Calandro, Enrico; Performance barriers to cloud services in Africas public sector: A latency perspective, International Conference on e-Infrastructure and e-Services for Developing Countries 152-163 2018 Springer, Cham
- 15. Singh, Siddharth; Nanda, Vedant; Sen, Rijurekha; Ahmad, Sohaib; Sengupta, Satadal; Phokeer, Amreesh; Farooq, Zaid Ahmed; Khan, Taslim Arefin; Kumaragaguru, Ponnurangam; Qazi, Ihsan Ayyub; An empirical analysis of facebook's free basics, Proceedings of the 2017 ACM SIGMETRICS/International Conference on Measurement and Modeling of Computer Systems 37-38 2017
- Chavula, Josiah; Phokeer, Amreesh; Formoso, Agustin; Feamster, Nick; Insight into Africa's country-level latencies, 2017 IEEE AFRICON 938-944 2017 IEEE
- 17. Sen, Rijurekha; Pirzada, Hasnain Ali; **Phokeer, Amreesh**; Farooq, Zaid Ahmed; Sengupta, Satadal; Choffnes, David; Gummadi, Krishna P; On the free bridge across the digital divide: Assessing the quality of facebook's free basics service, Proceedings of the 2016 Internet Measurement Conference 127-133 2016
- 18. Hadzic, Senka; **Phokeer, Amreesh**; Johnson, David; TownshipNet: A localized hybrid TVWS-WiFi and cloud services network, 2016 IEEE International Symposium on Technology and Society (ISTAS) 01-Jun 2016 IEEE
- 19. **Phokeer, Amreesh**; Densmore, Melissa; Johnson, David; Feamster, Nick; A first look at mobile internet use in township communities in South Africa, Proceedings of the 7th Annual Symposium on Computing for Development 01-Oct 2016

- 20. Phokeer, Amreesh; Aina, Alain; Johnson, David; DNS Lame delegations: A case-study of public reverse DNS records in the African Region, International Conference on e-Infrastructure and e-Services for Developing Countries 232-242 2016 Springer, Cham
- 21. **Phokeer, Amreesh**; Aina, Alain; A survey of anti-spam mechanisms and their usage from a Regional Internet Registry's perspective, 2016 IST-Africa Week Conference 01-Nov 2016 IEEE

Posters

- Phokeer, Amreesh; Hadzic, Senka; Nitschke, Eric; Van Zyl, Andre; Johnson, David; Densmore, Melissa; Chavula, Josiah; iNethi Community Network: A first look at local and Internet traffic usage, Proceedings of the 3rd ACM SIGCAS Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies 342-344 2020
- 2. Calandro, Enrico; Chavula, Josiah; **Phokeer, Amreesh**; The impact of remote hosting on Internet performance, 2018 CPRSOUTH

Honors

Fellowships

•	Heidelberg Laureate Forum	Sep 2023
•	CISPA Research Fellowship	Apr 2022

Awards

• IEEE INFOCOM 2018 Best-in-Session Presentation Award	May 2018
• IEEE AFRICON 2017 Most Outstanding Paper Award	Nov 2017

Scholarships

•	PhD Scholarship from Hasso-Plattner Institute, Germany	Feb 2016 - Jun 2019
•	Royal Holloway Scholarship for MSc in Information Security	Dec 2012 - Dec 2013
•	Merit French Government postgraduate Scholarship	Jun 2005 - Jul 2008

Other

•	Ranked 16th at	National A-Level	Cambridge Exams in Mauritius	Feb 2003
---	----------------	------------------	------------------------------	----------

SUPERVISORY & TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Ph.D. Project Supervision

• Martin Thody (Uni. of Cape Town, co-advised by Josiah Chavula) 2022 to Present

Pulse Research fellowship mentees

• Sadia Nourin (Uni. of Maryland, Topic: Censorship measurements)	2023
• Aravindh Raman (Telefonica Research, Topic: LEO satellite performance)	2023
• Alagappan Ramanathan (UC Irvine, Topic: Internet resilience)	2023

MANRS Research fellowship mentees

MANTO Research lenowship mentees	
• Thomas Holterbach (Uni. of Strasbourg, Topic: Forged origin hijacks)	2023
• Jediel Adefoulou (IFRI, Topic: MANRS Supply chain visualization)	2023
• Ioana Livadariu (Simula Research, Topic: RTBH and RPKI)	2022
• Tijay Chung (Virginia Tech, Topic: ROV measurements)	2022
• Zubair Sediqi (MPI, Topic: RPKI Validation measurements)	2022
• Romain Fontugne (IIJ Labs, Topic: Routing Security)	2021
• Dibya Khatiwada (PCH, Topic: Routing Security)	2021

M.S. Project Supervision

• CMU - ML-based approach to predict Internet Shutdowns	2023
• CMU - Using nightlights to infer Internet shutdowns	2023

	 CMU - Methods for understanding traffic locality CMU - Internet Resilience Composite Indicator 	$2022 \\ 2021$	
	 Teaching Assistant Networking course, University of Cape Town Measurements and Internet Protocol, University of Cape Town 	Feb 2017 June 2017	
Software Skills	 Computer Programming C, C++, Java, JavaScript, Python, Perl, PHP, UNIX shell scripting and others Jupyter, pandas, numpy R, matplotlib, d3 		
Memberships	 IEEE Membership IEEE Communication Society Membership Internet Society Membership 		
Languages	EnglishFrench	Fluent Native	
References	Available upon request.		